#5: Keyframes
#5: 关键帧
Our character is ready and now we are going to create a simple animation.
我们的角色准备好了，现在准备创建一段简单的动画。
Here, he is raising his left arm and then the right one.
这里，它举起左臂，接着是右臂。
Looks simple? Let's take a try.
看着很简单？我们试一试。
Suppose, our character lifts his right arm in 10 frames...
按设定，我们的角色在第10帧举起左臂...
...and then the left arm in other 10 frames.
...再过10帧举起右臂。
It would be more convenient to change the scale of Timetrack.
拉伸放大时间轴(Timetrack)会舒服点。
Move the mouse cursor over the gray rule and scroll the wheel.  Like this.
移动鼠标光标到灰色尺上面滚动鼠标滚轮。类似这样。
Now, let's switch to the Animation Mode.
现在我们切换到动画模式去。
Next, set the time cursor to the moment when the character should have his left arm raised - frame 10.
接着，设定时间光标到角色要举起左手的地方 - 第10帧。
And rotate the arm.
旋转手臂。
After that the second arm should start moving.
之后第二条手臂开始动。
Move the time cursor by 10 more frames.
移动时间光标10帧。
And now rotate his right arm.
再旋转他的右臂。
Let's check the result.
检查一下结果。
Oh, it looks like something is wrong.
哦，看起来有问题。
Both hands start moving simultaneously from the zero frame...
两只手在零帧处就同时动了...
...while we need the movements happen one after another.
...然而我们需要的动作是一个接一个的。
This happens because the position of the second hand in frame 10 isn't fixated.
这种情况的出现是因为第二只手在第10帧的地方没有固定。
That's why is starts moving right from the beginning.
这是为什么会在一开始右手就移动的原因。
It's easy to fix - just move this waypoint to the frame 10.
这个很容易修复的 - 只要移动这个航点到第10帧。
Now it works.
现在可以了。
Since this character is very simple, the issue is easy to fix.
因为这个角色很简单，这个问题很容易修复。
But in general case we have to work with much more complex characters, constructed from a dozens of layers...
但通常我们要处理的是复杂得多的角色，它由一堆层构成...
...and each scene could have several of them.
...而且每个场景都有多个角色。
And each layer can have many parameters we need to keep an eye on.
每一层也有很多参数我们要注意的。
Obviously we need some functionality to manage animation on a higher level.
显然我们要某些功能在一个更高的层面来管理动画。
For this purpose we have Keyframes.
对这种要求我们有关键帧(Keyframes)。
Keyframes are often confused with waypoints but in Synfig they're not the same thing.
关键帧经常会和航点混淆，但在 Synfig 中它们不是同一个东西。
Waypoints remembers a value of particular parameter at particular moment of time.
航点记住的是特定参数在特定时刻的值。
While keyframes, are also linked to a particular moment, but remember the state of all layers at once.
而对于关键帧，虽然它也是链接到一个特定时刻，但它一次性记住了所有层的状态。
Let's see how it works.
我们看看它是如何运作的。
Let's try to re-create our animation from scratch.
我们试着从头开始再创建我们的动画
First, we have to remove animation of both arms.
首先，我们要删掉两只手臂的动画。
We already know how to delete waypoints one by one.
我们已经知道如何一个一个的删除航点。
And also you can remove all waypoints for a parameter.
其实我们也可以一次删除某个参数的所有航点。
Just right-click a parameter and choose "Disconnect".
右键点击某个参数并选择“不链接(Disconnect)”。
This method is especially useful when we have many waypoints.
这种方法在多个航点的情况下特别的有用。
OK, we have all animation removed. So let's start.
好，我们把所有动画都删掉了。可以开始。
Keyframes are located on the blue strip, right here.
关键帧在这个绿色条上放着，就是这里。
Every Synfig animation have first keyframe created automatically, here it is.
每一个 Synfig 动画都会自动创建好第一个关键帧，就是这个。
Our character stands at the initial position.
我们的角色站在初始位置。
Let's make sure that the Animation Mode is enabled and go to the 10th frame.
确保动画模式打开，转到第10帧。
By the way, here you can use a special key combination - hold Ctrl and dot key to move time cursor one frame forward.
顺便说一下，你可以用特殊的辅助键混合 - 按住 Ctrl 键和点键向前移动一帧。
Now create a new keyframe.
现在创建一个新关键帧。
Right click...
右键点击...
Here we have a keyframe.
我们得到一个关键帧。
Let's rotate the left arm.
我们旋转左臂。
Done. Now let's get 10 more frames forward...
完成。现在我们再前进10帧。
create a new keyframe...
创建一个新关键帧...
and rotate the second arm.
旋转第二只手臂。
Note that Synfig has added an extra waypoint to preserve the object state at the previous keyframe.
注意 Synfig 已经多添加了一个航点用来保护前一帧的物体状态。
Now the animation looks as expected without any additional fixes.
现在动画已经如我们所期望的那样了，不用什么额外的工作。
Let's take a look at one more example of how keyframes work.
我们再举的一个例子来解释一下关键帧的工作方式。
Let's create a new file.
我们创建一个新文件。
This will be animation of a ball moving up and then back down.
做个球上升然后下来的动画。
We already have one keyframe by default.
在默认情况下，我们已经有个关键帧。
It is used to remember the state of objects in the very beginning.
它用来记住在最开始的物体状态。
Create two more keyframes.
再创建多两个关键帧。
Go to the second keyframe, enable the animation mode...
到第二帧，打开动画模式...
...and move the ball upwards.
...然后把球向上移。
Now, 3 waypoints have appeared.
现在，出现3个航点。
The middle waypoint was created because we set new position of the ball in animation mode.
中间航点的出现是因为我们在动画模式下给球设置了新位置。
And two others were automatically created to save the ball's keyframe positions.
另外两个航点也是自动创建的，用来保存球在关键帧处的位置。
So, the ball jumps upwards and falls back down.
所以，球挑起来再落下。
Synfig also have a special panel with a list of keyframes.
Synfig 还有一个特殊的面板，上面有关键帧列表。
Here you can name each keyframe...
在这里你可以给每一个关键帧命名...
...and quickly jump from one keyframe to another.
...还能快速的从一个关键帧跳到另一个关键帧。
Just click the "Jump" label here.
只要点击这里的“跳跃(Jump)” 标签。
It is very similar to a link in a web browser.
这和网络浏览器离得链接非常类似。
Now I'd like to illustrate how keyframes help to manipulate waypoints.
现在我要阐述一下关键帧是如何在操纵航点时起作用的。
Let's get back to our character.
我们回到角色。
Here we have two objects animated - one arm and the other arm.
我们有两个动的物体 - 一个是手臂，一个是另一条手臂。
If we move a keyframe... all waypoints at this time location are moved as well.
如果我们移动一个关键帧... 在这个时间点位置的所有航点也随着一起移动。
We don't even need to select the objects.
我们甚至不需选择任何物体。
Sometimes you might need to move a keyframe together with all its subsequent keyframes.
有时候你也许需要一起移动某个关键帧和它的后续关键帧。
In this case, just hold Alt and Shift keys when you move it. Like this.
这种情况，只要在移动时按下 Alt 和Shift 键就可以。像这样。
We can copy keyframes from one moment to another. Just as we could with waypoints.
我们可以从某个时刻把关键帧拷贝到另一时刻去。这和航点是一样的。
For example, let's make our character return to initial pose at the frame 40.
比如，在第40帧时，我们把角色重置回初始的姿势。
Go to the frame 40...
转到第40帧...
...right-click this first keyframe...
...右键点击第一个关键帧...
...and choose "Duplicate".
...选择“复制(Duplicate)”。
As you can see, Synfig has created all required waypoints to put our character in the same pose as he was on the frame 0.
如你所见，Synfig已经创建了需要的用来重设角色回到第0帧姿势的所有航点。
Also it is not necessary to have the Animation Mode enabled when we manipulate the keyframes.
另外在处理关键帧时我们是不需要到动画模式下的。
And one more thing to consider:
还有一件事情要考虑的：
when we delete a keyframe all its waypoints would be also deleted. Take a look.
当我们删掉某个关键帧其下所有的航点也会被删掉。看一下。
Finally, I would like to show you one more powerful trick that we can do with keyframes.
最后，我要给你展示另外一个有用的关键帧技巧。
After frame number 40 let's make our character to wave with his hand.
在40帧后，我们让角色挥舞他的手。
But in this case I won't be placing a keyframe for each position.
但在这个例子中，我不想在每个位置上都放置关键帧。
Instead, I will put one keyframe at the start of the action...
放而，我打算放一个关键帧到动作的开始时刻...
...and one at the end.
...在结尾也放一个。
Done. Now I've got two events, two keyframes...
完工。现在我有了两个事件，两个关键帧...
the character started waving his hand... and he stopped waving.
角色开始挥舞他的手...然后停下来。
Now let's try to move the last keyframe.
现在让我们移动最后一个关键帧。
And here's the trick: moving keyframes automatically scales the waypoints between them.
这里有个技巧：移动关键帧会自动压缩或伸展它们之间的航点。
Look, how easy I can change duration of the whole action.
看，多容易，可以随意改变整个动作的长度。